Guide to the Alfred A. Hart Photographs PC0002
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Alfred A. Hart photographs
1862-1869
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hart, Alfred A., 1816-1908
PC0002
5.5 Linear Feet (1 album: 375 unbound photoprints: albumen; 375 photonegatives; 154 photoprints: stereograph, mounted)
Information about Access
Open for research.
Alternative Formats
The photographs have been digitized and are available online here: http://purl.stanford.edu/nj339gb1246#
Other Finding Aids
Indices (subject, title, geography, stereographs) are available online here: http://purl.stanford.edu/cr783ct0939.
Biographical/Historical note
Alfred A. Hart, born in Norwich, Connecticut on March 16, 1816, was the principal photographer for the Central Pacific Railroad during the construction of the Overland Route. He photographed the construction from 1865 to 1869 when the last spike was driven by Leland Stanford at Promontory, Utah on May 10, 1869.
Although he worked as a photographer as early as 1857, Hart was trained as a portrait and landscape artist; after his work for the Central Pacific, he continued to paint and was awarded the gold medal for his paintings at an exhibition at the California State Fair in 1872. Nonetheless, Hart is remembered for his work in visually documenting the construction of the western half of the first transcontinental railroad.
It is not clear just how Hart managed to be hired as principal photographer for the CPRR. Ironically, Carleton E. Watkins was a life-long friend of Collis P. Huntington (CPRR's business manager), and Watkins performed as a photographer for the railway after Hart's commission was completed. It is possible that Watkins was so well known during the time of the railroad construction that the Central Pacific may have thought his professional fees would have been more demanding than Alfred Hart's. Yet, according to Charles B. Turrill, photographer and biographer of Carleton Watkins, the friendship between Huntington and Watkins was so dear that bills and payments were of secondary consideration, and that Watkins did not require any payment for his services with the Central Pacific. Because we are lacking information about Hart and Watkins it is difficult to draw clear conclusions as to why Hart was given this opportunity instead of Watkins.
Hart quite clearly and consciously used his artistic talents while giving an honest representation of the railroad construction. Andrew Russell, photographer for the Union Pacific Railroad, undoubtedly attempted to bring art into the documentation of his portion of the railroad line, but he was at a circumstantial disadvantage because his route was more desolate. The terrain in Hart's territory was much more aesthetically pleasing, and offered a wider variety of back-drops to his construction scenes. While Russell focused much more on trains, construction and frontier towns along the way, Hart was able to turn his camera to mountain lakes and quiet river banks, giving his images a more universal appeal competitive with landscape photography of his day. Hart's highly artistic railroad views were much more than mere documentation; they were such fine examples of photographic imagery that they were able to help set a trend of producing stereo cards in special series independent of the railway commission and separate from large publishers. Selling his stereo views thus became a successful commercial endeavor.
Hart was working in a period when the wet collodion plate was the most modern process available. This cumbersome process was a vast improvement over the earlier daguerreotype in that it produced a more desirable image with a more realistic reproduction, even though the process itself was complicated. Collodion had to be applied evenly on a clean glass plate, which was sensitized in a bath of silver nitrate. Next, the photographer had to wait a few minutes to allow the bromides and iodides of the prepared collodion to react with the silver nitrate; then a minutes-long exposure was made while the plate was still wet. Removing the still-wet plate from the camera while in a darkened area, the photographer quickly poured developing solution evenly over the glass. From this point the glass had to be rinsed thoroughly with clean water, a commodity not always readily available to field photographers. The image was then fixed by immersing the plate in a solvent of silver iodide until the salts were freed. Again the glass had to be rinsed to rid it of all chemicals, and then it was dried by passing it over the heat of a lamp flame. Finally, the plate was varnished (while still warm from the lamp) in order to protect the emulsion.
In addition to all this hazardous chemical processing Alfred Hart had to endure, as a field photographer his equipment consisted of a view camera (probably about 18 by 22 inches from front to back), complete with tripod, plate holder and slides, all made from solid wood. Other items on his list of weighty, but essential, equipment were ground glass, lenses, shutters, glass plates, and a dark tent, all of which had to be transported above and beyond points reached by railroad workers.
After 1869 Hart continued to work as a photographer and moved around the country selling his photographs. Carleton Watkins acquired some of Hart's negatives in 1869 where they were kept in his San Francisco studio. Prints from the negatives were sold to the public. Unfortunately, Hart's negatives were destroyed the 1906 earthquake along with the rest of Watkins' studio, but not before enough prints had been produced and sold to allow for the survival of most of the Central Pacific Railroad collection.
From 1872 to 1878 Hart worked in San Francisco as a portrait and landscape painter. He died on March 5, 1908 at the Alameda County Infirmary.
[Taken from Mary Blessing's essay,"Alfred A. Hart: Frontier Photographer," 1979]
For more information about Hart and his photographic techniques, see Glenn Willumson's master's thesis Alfred A. Hart: Photographer of the Transcontinental Railroad. (UC Davis, 1984)
Scope and Contents note
The Alfred A. Hart Collection includes one photograph album of 365 images, and 106 stereographs. The majority of the stereographs are duplicate images from the album. However, there are also ten stereographs of the home of Leland and Jane Stanford in Sacramento (images that do not appear in the album).
The album measures 33 cm x 27 cm x 6 cm (13" x 10.5" x 2.5") and has been disbound (The binding has not survived.). There are 49 gilt-edged boards, constituting 94 pages of photographs. There are 4 photographs per page. The photographs have been arranged in geographic order, from California to Utah. Some of the pages have fewer than four photographs. These are:
Page 6: 2 photographs only Page 65: 1 photograph only Page 70: 3 photographs only Page 71: 1 photograph only Page 94: 3 photographs only
There are four blank pages in the album that were not numbered:
--Between pages 59 and 60 --Between pages 70 and 71 --Between pages 71 and 72 --Between pages 74 and 75
The numbered stereographs are arranged numerically in four boxes. The fifth stereograph box contains the ten photographs of the Stanford family house in Sacramento (interior and exterior views). There are two stereographic images that do not appear in the album. These are #489 ("Snow Scene in the Mountains") and #494 ("Snow Shoes"). For better access to the images, the photographs in the album have been indexed in an online catalogue with the following seven fields:
1) Image number 2) Title of image 3) Subjects 4) Geographic sequence number 5) Geographic area 6) Existence of a stereograph for the album images 7) Page number of the album
The records for these fields have been sorted, and these reports constitute the core of the guide to the Hart collection.
The image numbers, titles, and geographic areas were assigned by Hart. The geographic sequence number, subjects, indication as to whether a stereograph exists for an image, and the page numbers of the album, were assigned by the indexer.
Image number
Each photograph has a unique number assigned by Hart. The following numbers were not used by Hart in the album at Stanford University: 208, 219, 238, 253, 306, 307, 308, 309. There are also two photographs numbered"275." For indexing purposes, these have been assigned the numbers"275a" and"275b." These photographs are both entitled "Eagle Gap. Truckee River" but each is a unique view.
Title of image
Each photograph has a title assigned by Hart. Often the altitude and distance from Sacramento is included.
Subjects
The Hart photographs richly illustrate people, places, and things: the construction of a nineteenth-century railroad in all its phases (excavations of the road, grading, track laying, trestle construction, tunnel digging, etc.); locomotives; train cars (boxcars, flatcars, cabooses, etc.); laborers (Caucasian and Chinese); Native Americans; topographic features (mountains, valleys, deserts, rivers, lakes); and frontier town scenes. To help make these images accessible to researchers of wide-ranging interests, subjects have been used to index them. The number of subjects varies according to what was captured in the photograph. For example, image #26 is a simple photograph of a ravine, and"Auburn Ravine" is the only subject given to this photograph. On the other hand, #211 "West Portal Tunnel No. 1, Grizzly Hill" (which includes a train), has been assigned many subjects: "Tunnel No. 1," "Grizzly Hill," "Locomotive," "Boxcar," and "Combine car."
In addition to named mountains, rivers, lakes, towns, and people, the following subject words are used:
Boxcar Boy Brewery Bridge Caboose Camera and photographer Camp Canyon Chinese Combine car Culvert Depot Embankment Excursion party Flatcar Girl Handcar Indian Laborers Lake Locomotive Lumberyard Palisades Passengers Quarry Ravine River Sawmill Snowbank Snowplow Snowshed Stagecoach Teamsters Telegraph pole Train Trestle Tunnel Turntable Valley Wagon road Wagon train Wagons Water tank Water train Waterfall
Geographic sequence number
Hart did not take the photographs in precise chronological or geographic order, but for presentation of the images in the album, he arranged them geographically from the start of construction in Sacramento to the completion in Promontory, Utah. Thus, image #1, a photograph of the locomotive Governor Stanford, happens to appear as the twenty-second photograph on album page seven. Another example, image #234, a view of the wharves in Sacramento, is the first image on page one of the album.
To assist the user who is interested in the geographic element of the photographs, and/or the geographic progression of the images, a geographic sequence number was given each photograph. In this way, other subjects of the photograph can be linked to the geographic area and sequencing of each photograph, such as mountains, deserts, valleys, rivers.
There are four photographs per page, and the geographic sequence numbering begins on the top left, to the top right, to the bottom left, to the bottom right, in this manner: G-1, G-2, G-3, G-4 on page one; G-5, G-6, G-7, G-8 on page two, etc. For example, G-1 (#234) is "Railroad Wharves at Sacramento City." G-168 (#99) is "Cisco, Placer County." G-289 (#284) is "Freight Depots at Reno," and the last photograph in the album is G-365 (#364), "Railroad at Ogden, Wahsatch Range in Distance."
Geographic area
Each photograph is included in one of seven broad geographic areas, assigned by Hart. These are:
1)"Valley of the Sacramento" 2)"Sierra Nevada Mountains, Western Summit" 3)"Sierra Nevada Mountains, Donner Lake" 4)"Sierra Nevada Mountains, Truckee River, Eastern Summit" 5)"Washoe Range, Truckee River" 6)"Humboldt River, The Desert" 7)"Wahsatch Range, Great Salt Lake"
Stereograph
Hart had stereographs made for several of the images that appear in the album. To indicate whether a stereograph exists for any particular image, a simple"yes" or"no" was used.
Page number of album
Each album page was numbered, and each photograph has its page number associated with it in the index.
Central Pacific Railroad; Railroads; California -- Description and travel -- Views.; Photographs.; Central Pacific Railroad--Construction; Hart, Alfred A., 1816-1908; Hart, Alfred A., 1816-1908; Kamena, Ruth M.
- Prints, Series 1
  - Photograph album
    - Locomotive, Gov. Stanford, No. 1., 1 (Box 1)
      General note
      Subjects:
      Locomotive; Governor Stanford
      Geographic sequence:
      G-23
      Geographic area:
      Sierra Nevada Mountains, Western Summit
      Page number:
      7
      Stereograph?
      Yes
    - Trestle at Newcastle, Placer County., 2 (Box 1)
      Trestle; Locomotive; Boxcar; Combine car; Train
      G-24
      No
    - View of Newcastle, 31 miles from Sacramento., 3 (Box 1)
      Trestle; Newcastle, California
      G-25
    - Road above Newcastle, Placer County., 4 (Box 1)
      Newcastle, California; telegraph pole
      G-26
    - View in Dutch Ravine, Placer County., 5 (Box 1)
      Dutch Ravine; telegraph pole
      G-27
      8
    - View in Dutch Ravine, 32 miles from Sacramento., 6 (Box 1)
      G-28
    - Embankment in Dutch Ravine, above Newcastle., 7 (Box 1)
      Dutch Ravine
      G-29
    - Approaching Bloomer Cut, from the West., 8 (Box 1)
      Bloomer Cut; telegraph pole
      G-30
    - Bloomer Cut, 800 feet long, looking East., 9 (Box 1)
      Bloomer Cut
      G-31
      9
    - Bloomer Cut, birdseye view, 63 feet deep, 880 long., 10 (Box 1)
      G-32
    - Bloomer Cut and Embankment, looking East., 11 (Box 1)
      G-33
    - Bloomer Cut, 63 feet high, looking West., 12 (Box 1)
      G-34
    - View in Bloomer Cut, near Auburn., 13 (Box 1)
      G-35
      10
    - Bloomer Cut, Eastern portion, 34 miles from Sacramento., 14 (Box 1)
      G-36
    - High Bank, Baltimore Ravine., 15 (Box 1)
      High Bank; Baltimore Ravine
      G-38
    - Rock Cut, near Auburn, Placer County., 16 (Box 1)
      Rock Cut; telegraph pole
      G-39
      11
    - Rock Ravine, near Auburn., 17 (Box 1)
      Rock Ravine; telegraph pole
      G-40
    - High Embankment, near Auburn., 18 (Box 1)
      Embankment; telegraph pole
      G-41
    - Trestle near Station, at Auburn., 19 (Box 1)
      Trestle; Auburn, California
      G-42
    - Cut near Auburn Station, Placer County., 20 (Box 1)
      Auburn, California
      G-43
      12
    - Auburn Depot, Altitude 1,385 feet. 36 miles from Sacramento., 21 (Box 1)
      Auburn, California; Depot; Locomotive; Flatcar
      G-44
    - Road East of Station, at Auburn., 22 (Box 1)
      G-45
    - Road in Auburn Ravine, Placer County., 23 (Box 1)
      Auburn Ravine; telegraph pole
      G-46
    - Lime Point, above Auburn., 24 (Box 1)
      Auburn, California; Lime Point
      G-47
      13
    - High Embankment, Auburn Ravine., 25 (Box 1)
      Auburn Ravine; Embankment; telegraph pole
      G-48
    - Auburn Ravine, Placer County., 26 (Box 1)
      G-49
    - Trestle near Lovell’s Ranch, 40 miles from Sacramento., 27 (Box 1)
      Trestle; Lovell’s Ranch
      G-50
    - Road and Trestle, near Lovell’s Ranch., 28 (Box 1)
      Trestle
      G-51
      14
    - Trestle in Clipper Ravine, near Clipper Gap., 29 (Box 1)
      Trestle; Clipper Ravine
      G-52
    - Trestle Bridge, 120 feet high, 600 feet long, Clipper Ravine., 30 (Box 1)
      Trestle; bridge; Clipper Ravine
      G-53
    - Trestle Bridge, Clipper Ravine, near view., 31 (Box 1)
      G-54
    - View above Clipper Gap, Placer County., 32 (Box 1)
      Clipper Gap, California
      G-57
      15
    - Locomotive Nevada, at Colfax, Placer County., 33 (Box 1)
      Locomotive; Nevada; Colfax, California
      G-59
      16
    - Locomotive Atlantic, at Colfax, Placer County., 34 (Box 1)
      Locomotive; Atlantic; Colfax, California; Depot
      G-60
    - Depot at Colfax, 500 feet long, 55 miles from Sacramento., 35 (Box 1)
      Colfax, California; Depot; Boxcar; Flatcar
      G-61
    - Colfax from the South, Altitude 2,448 feet., 36 (Box 1)
      Colfax, California; Teamsters; Wagons
      G-62
    - Teamster’s Camp, at Colfax, Placer County., 37 (Box 1)
      G-63
      17
    - Canyon of American River from near Colfax. Cape Horn and the Railroad on the left., 38 (Box 1)
      American River Canyon; Cape Horn
      G-66
    - Long Ravine Bridge, from the top of Cape Horn., 39 (Box 1)
      Long Ravine; Bridge
      G-67
      18
    - Long Ravine Bridge from the West, 56 miles from Sacramento., 40 (Box 1)
      G-68
    - Long Ravine Bridge, near Colfax. Length 1,050 feet., 41 (Box 1)
      Long Ravine; Bridge; Flatcar
      G-69
    - Long Ravine Bridge from below, 120 feet high., 42 (Box 1)
      Long Ravine; Bridge; Locomotive; Flatcar; Boxcar
      G-70
    - Cape Horn and Railroad from West, Height above Ravine 1,400 feet., 43 (Box 1)
      Cape Horn
      G-71
      19
    - American River and Canyon from Cape Horn. River below Railroad 1,400 feet. 57 miles from Sac., 44 (Box 1)
      American River; Cape Horn; Locomotive; Flatcar
      G-78
      20
    - Sawmill and Cut East of Cape Horn, 59 miles from Sacramento., 45 (Box 1)
      Sawmill
      G-81
      21
    - Deep cut at Trail Ridge. Length 1,000 feet., 46 (Box 1)
      Trail Ridge
      G-82
    - Secrettown, 62 miles from Sacramento. Altitude 3,000 feet., 47 (Box 1)
      Secrettown, California
      G-83
      22
    - Secrettown Trestle from the West. Length 1,100 feet., 48 (Box 1)
      Secrettown Trestle
      G-85
    - Secrettown Trestle from the East. Hight 90 feet., 49 (Box 1)
      G-86
    - Tunnel Hill Cut. Depth 111 feet. 63 miles from Sacramento., 50 (Box 1)
      Tunnel Hill
      G-87
      23
    - Bear River Valley, near Gold Run. You Bet and Mines in the distance., 51 (Box 1)
      Bear River Valley; You Bet
      G-88
    - Bear River Valley, near Gold Run. Little York and mines in the distance., 52 (Box 1)
      Bear River Valley; Little York mines
      G-89
    - Cut through “Dixie Spur.” 64 miles from Sacramento., 53 (Box 1)
      Dixie Spur; Teamsters
      G-91
      24
    - Gold Run and Railroad Cut. Altitude 3,245 feet., 54 (Box 1)
      Gold Run, California; Teamsters
      G-93
      Sierra Nevada Mountains
    - Flume and Railroad at Gold Run. 64 miles from Sacramento., 55 (Box 1)
      Flume; Gold Run, California; Rackett Hotel; Aldrich, Geo. D.
      G-94
    - Rounding Cape Horn. Road to Iowa Hill from the River, in the distance., 56 (Box 1)
      Cape Horn; Locomotive; Iowa Hill, California; telegraph pole
      G-75
    - Excursion Train at Cape Horn. 3 miles above Colfax., 57 (Box 1)
      Cape Horn; Locomotive; Passengers; Excusion Party
      G-76
    - Secret Ravine. Iowa Hill in the distance. 61 miles from Sacramento., 58 (Box 1)
      Secret Ravine; Locomotive; Flatcar; Iowa Hill, California
      G-77
    - Hornet Hill Cut, West of Gold Run. 50 feet deep., 59 (Box 1)
      Hornet Hill
      G-90
    - Train at Dixie Cut. Gold Run Station, Placer County., 60 (Box 1)
      Dixie Cut; Locomotive; Boxcar; Teamsters
      G-92
    - Hydraulic Mining, at Gold Run, Placer County., 61 (Box 1)
      Hydraulic mining; Gold Run, California
      G-95
      25
    - Embankment below Dutch Flat, Placer County., 62 (Box 1)
      Embankment; Locomotive; Boxcar
      G-96
    - Dutch Flat, Placer County. 67 miles from Sacramento., 63 (Box 1)
      Dutch Flat, California
      G-97
    - Dutch Flat Station. 67 miles from Sacramento. Altitude 3,416 feet., 64 (Box 1)
      G-98
    - Forest View, near Dutch Flat, Placer County., 65 (Box 1)
      G-99
      26
    - Sandstone Cut, near Alta, Placer County., 66 (Box 1)
      Sandstone
      G-100
    - Alta from the South. Altitude 3,635 feet. 69 miles from Sacramento., 67 (Box 1)
      Locomotive; Flatcar; Alta, California
      G-101
    - Alta from the North. Altitude 3,635 feet. 69 miles from Sacramento., 68 (Box 1)
      Locomotive; Alta, California
      G-102
    - Huntington at Alta, Placer County., 69 (Box 1)
      Locomotive; C.P. Huntington; Alta, California; Depot
      G-103
      27
    - Blasting at Chalk Bluffs above Alta. Cut 60 feet deep., 70 (Box 1)
      Chinese; Laborers; Chalk bluffs
      G-106
    - Building Bank across Canyon Creek. 87 feet high., 71 (Box 1)
      Chinese; Laborers; Teamsters; Canyon Creek
      G-107
      28
    - Culvert at Canyon Creek. 185 feet long--12 feet span., 72 (Box 1)
      Culvert; Canyon Creek
      G-108
    - Cut above Alta, Placer County., 73 (Box 1)
      Alta, California
      G-105
    - Secrettown Bridge. 1,100 feet long. 62 miles from Sacramento., 74 (Box 1)
      Secrettown Bridge; Trestle
      G-84
    - Superintendent Strobridge and Family, at Alta., 75 (Box 1)
      Strobridge, J. H.; Alta, California
      G-104
    - Giant’s Gap, American River, 2,500 feet perpendicular. 72 miles from Sacramento., 76 (Box 1)
      Giant’s Gap; American River; Canyon
      G-111
      29
    - Green Valley and Giant’s Gap. American River 1,500 feet below Railroad., 77 (Box 1)
      Green Valley; Giant’s Gap; Canyon; American River
      G-110
    - Green Bluffs. 1,500 feet above American River. 71 miles from Sacramento., 78 (Box 1)
      Green Bluffs; American River
      G-112
    - View West of Prospect Hill. 75 miles from Sacramento., 79 (Box 1)
      Prospect Hill
      G-116
      30
    - Prospect Hill from Camp 21. 75 miles from Sacramento., 80 (Box 1)
      Prospect Hill; Camp 21
      G-117
    - Little Blue Canyon. 74 miles from Sacramento., 81 (Box 1)
      Little Blue Canyon
      G-115
    - Prospect Hill Cut. Upper slope, 170 feet., 82 (Box 1)
      Prospect Hill; Chinese; Laborers; Teamsters; Wagons
      G-118
    - Prospect Hill Cut, from the North., 83 (Box 1)
      G-119
      31
    - View at China Ranch. 75 miles from Sacramento., 84 (Box 1)
      China Ranch
      G-122
    - Fort Point Cut. 70 feet deep, 600 feet long., 85 (Box 1)
      Fort Point
      G-124
      32
    - View North of Fort Point. 76 miles from Sacramento., 86 (Box 1)
      G-125
    - Horse Ravine. 77 miles from Sacramento., 87 (Box 1)
      Horse Ravine
      G-126
    - Horse Ravine Wall, and Grizzly Hill Tunnel. 77 miles from Sacramento., 88 (Box 1)
      Horse Ravine; Grizzly Hill Tunnel; Tunnel No. 01; Teamsters
      G-127
      33
    - Grizzly Hill Tunnel from the North. 500 feet long., 89 (Box 1)
      Grizzly Hill Tunnel; Tunnel No. 01
      G-128
    - Bank and Cut at Sailor’s Spur. 80 miles from Sacramento., 90 (Box 1)
      Sailor’s Spur; Teamsters; Wagons
      G-134
      34
    - Owl Gap Cut. 900 feet long, 45 feet deep. 80 miles from Sacramento., 91 (Box 1)
      Owl Gap Cut; Teamsters; Wagons
      G-135
      35
    - Heath’s Ravine Bank. 80 feet high. 82 miles from Sacramento., 92 (Box 1)
      Heath’s Ravine Bank; Teamsters; Wagons
      G-137
    - Black Butte and Crystal Lake. 90 miles from Sacramento., 93 (Box 1)
      Black Butte; Crystal Lake Houe
      G-159
      41
    - Crystal Lake. Altitude 5,907 feet. 90 miles from Sacramento., 94 (Box 1)
      Crystal Lake House; Hart, Alfred A. [?]
      G-160
    - Crystal Lake House. 90 miles from Sacramento., 95 (Box 1)
      Crystal Lake House; Teamsters; Wagons
      G-161
    - Cascades of the Yuba River, near Crystal Lake., 96 (Box 1)
      Yuba River
      G-162
    - Rattlesnake Mountain and Cascades on Yuba River, near Cisco., 97 (Box 1)
      Rattlesnake Mountain; Yuba River
      G-163
      42
    - Black Butte, from the North., 98 (Box 1)
      Black Butte
      G-164
    - Cisco, Placer County. 92 miles from Sacramento., 99 (Box 1)
      Sacramento Brewery Depot, C. Shafer; Cisco, California
      G-168
      43
    - Yuba Cascade and Hieroglyphic Rocks, on the Yuba River, near Crystal Lake., 100 (Box 1)
      Yuba River; Hieroglyphic Rocks; Crystal Lake